foreign
hello and welcome everyone it's December
7th
2022. this is active inference live
stream number 31.1
we are here with Brett Kagan and we're
going to be hearing a presentation and
having a discussion on free energy
principle and active inference in
synthetic biological intelligence we'll
have a presentation followed by a
discussion so feel free to submit any
questions if you would like Brett thank
you for joining really looking forward
to this presentation and discussion off
to you
thanks so much Daniel and thank you
everyone for joining us today hopefully
we've got some interesting stuff so what
I want to talk to you about is the work
that we've been doing uh in what we call
synthetic biological intelligence and
particularly the use we've made of uh
principles from the free energy
principle and active inference
Frameworks
so
if we jump to sort of the first question
and we can kind of ask ourselves because
we work with neural systems what is
there that's unique about neural systems
and one of the obvious answers to that
is that they display this unique ability
to collate information and apply it in
an Adaptive behavior in multiple
contexts and that could be a fitting
definition for intelligence if you like
um but to actually be able to test this
in actual sales in real time what you
have to do is be able to record the
information from the cells and provide
information back to the cells in real
time
so how did we go about setting this up
how did we get these cells so we did it
in two ways
either we took what's called a human
induced pluripotent stem cell that's the
hip SC there that you can see and what
you can do is develop these from any
donor blood tissue or skin and you can
basically make a pluripotent stem cell
line and then you can use a number of
different methods to turn that into
neurons of you know quite a degree of
specificity we used quite a broad one
for most of our work which is called a
dual somat inhibition which follows like
natural ontological development uh on
antigenine development I should say uh
to uh sort of create these predominantly
cortical cultures uh in a dish but you
can use other direct methods such as
what's called an ngn2 direct
differentiation which gives rise to a
more excitatory culture
uh then we also took a primary cortical
neural cultures for Mouse and we grew
them as a comparison because we wanted
to make sure that we were using at least
in some sense bona fide cortical neurons
and the best way to do that is to take
it from animals uh but fortunately as
you see we will be able to move and we
have moved away from that now in our
current practice so we're completely uh
animal testing free at the moment
uh and then what we did was we plated
these onto what's called a high density
multi-electrode array and essentially
I'll show you a bit more of this in a
second this is essentially a CMOS chip
which is a type of Chip that you might
get in a digital camera
but it's also can be used in this
purpose because what it can do is sense
electrical signals even very small ones
and actually be able to stimulate to
them
and so just some evidence that we we
actually did do the work we said we did
here's some examples of some cultures
that we've grown and they show uh what
we're able to do is use techniques to
actually capture key markers of aspects
of these cells so for example this uh
blue over here hopefully it's coming up
or right on your screens this shows
something called dappy which marks all
the nucleus of every any cell uh if you
want you can look at something called
new and here new and marks neurons so
all the green dots and you might be able
to see a bit better in this picture or
the green dots show that this is
actually a neuron
and then of course one of the things
that we know neurons have is that they
send out uh axons and that's what this
thing called beta3 tubulin marks in the
red and finally we want to know do they
have dendrites and you can see here in
the purple this is marking dendrites
also a little bit of axons but it also
marks dendrites as well and then more
than that we want to know is not just
are they neurons because on your or most
neurons will have those traits but also
are they cortical neurons and uh brn1 is
actually a marker for cortical neuron so
you can see here actually not only are
they neurons but most of those neurons
are cortical uh specifically there's of
course going to be different cell types
in there for example gfap here Mark
supporting cell types such as collia and
you can see here we have a number of
glia you can also really obviously see
that these glia these in the bigger
picture have quite a different
morphology than the neurons
so it's nice that we have sort of this
mixed population because it means that
we're able to test something that has
some degree of uh you know comparable uh
characteristics to what you might see in
the uh cortical you know in an animal or
now quarter cortical uh areas
uh of course it's much much simpler
magnitude and magnitude simpler than
that but it is you know reassuring for
the function to know that there are some
uh similarities as a model and
importantly for anyone who has looked at
sort of creating cells out of stem cells
one of the big problems is that not all
of those cells might be fully
differentiated and if you do have cells
that aren't differentiated and still
polypodent when you put them in a dish
they can turn into anything and of
course most of the time what they turn
into something uh invasive and
potentially cancerous depending what it
is fortunately this ki-67 marks dividing
cells so this would sort of Mark any
cell that wasn't uh fully differentiated
and we had uh this is a case where we
had none of them and that was common but
generally we had none to very very few
and because of that we're actually able
to have these cultures growing for
extended periods of time and this is
what's a cryoscanning electron
microscopy image so these are real
biological neurons they're a little
cracked because when you do the the cryo
aspect of the scanning and you phrase
them uh for the necessary preparation
they do tend to crack a bit but you can
still mostly see that there are a lot of
intact neurons a lot of connections and
then behind that you can actually see
all the electrodes and you can also see
the density and the complexity of this
and this is actually an area of the chip
that is less dense and and
interconnected than some of the other
areas because if you look at the ones
that are highly dense and connected you
can't see the the chip behind him we
kind of wanted to show the fact that
there's a chip behind this uh and I
think like one of the key things to take
away from this simply is the degree of
complexity you get here compared to
something like an artificial neural
network a lot of the time people look at
models and they're quite nice and neat
and symmetrical and that's just not what
happens in biology and as we'll discuss
later there's there's probably some
interesting features that arise out of
this degree and this extent of uh random
or pseudo-random connectivity
and so what we could then do with this
technology is map out this is an example
of like the chip surface and then the
firing rate in hertz can be seen here as
a color scale and we can see over time
with different cell types we can get
their activity and different cell types
sort of turn on or begin to become
active at different times but
importantly what we can do is get a
fairly even distribution of active cells
over the surface area fairly
consistently again anyone who works in
this area knows there's a fair bit of
variation inherently and that stuff
we're working on now for the future but
we are able to get this degree of um
of activity over time and that gives us
some useful cell cultures to test
of course uh how do we go about testing
that which is the big question and uh we
know that as a living organism you me
mice cats whatever we need to have a
closed-loop feedback to operate and what
does that mean essentially it means that
we're able to uh receive information
about the outcomes of our actions and
modify our actions as a result of it so
if I reach over for a cell phone I
immediately get sensory feedback in a
number of modalities to as I do that
action and as I pick it up I'm aware of
the success of it if I fail I'm aware of
that too and this is actually this
little mouse with a VR headset on is
from this athenshire study which is one
of my favorite studies that's been done
in recent times where they actually
attach it to their virtual reality to
mice and they found that if they
disconnected the mouse's movement as it
was developing from the actual visual
information it got it led to quite
catastrophic uh developmental functional
developmental impairments and it just
really shows it shouldn't be surprising
so much but it does show us like that
this link with our environment is
incredibly important for us as organisms
uh to develop and so if you're looking
at cells in a dish and you want to try
and elicit intelligence you can
immediately say well you need to have
some sort of linkage some embodiment
which is achieved through this closed
loop system uh to be set up and so like
one of the better ways to sort of do
this is to contrast with an open
feedback system because that's what
people generally do so just to emphasize
this closely it means that we stimulate
some sort of sensation and that can be
done with an electrical stimulation and
we can provide then sensory feedback
again through electrical stimulation on
how that response Alters the world and
it's actually been demonstrated before
in a few studies for example and it's
back in paper that this closed loop
stimulation does result in increased
plasticity
um
but we wanted to try and take it a
little further and actually see if we
could elicit a very clear gold directed
behavior and so we set up this is a
little schematic of the dish and what we
did was we almost arbitrarily defined uh
that there are I shouldn't say cyber
Terry because there was a lot of uh
planning and strategy behind it but what
I mean by this is that within a given
framework for example here what we did
was we designated a sensory region where
we put information into electrodes using
a combination of rate and place coding
and then we read it out in a sort of
counterbalanced region here so activity
in in these two regions would make the
paddle move up activity and these two
regions would make the paddle move down
uh but the reason I say it's arbitrary
was that we were able to uh
basically change this configuration to a
number of ways and for the most part
although there were some differences get
a degree of statistically significant
performance and that of course just
shows the fact that neurons as again
shouldn't be a surprise to anybody are
incredibly plastic and able to adapt and
change uh how they respond uh otherwise
and I think that's the real interesting
thing because of course starting out
here there is no real reason why neurons
should behave in any particular way
unless they're doing it to a call to
some fundamental imperative
uh and this is just an example of the
visualization you're actually able to go
uh there's a there's a site if you jump
to our website I'll show that later it's
called Spike stream and you can go and
play around with this yourself it's
available so this is an example of the
electrode uh multilateral Ray each
Little Dot is a potential electrode we
can route the blue ones are the ones
we're routing at the moment each little
bar is a activity and you can see we put
activity in the top and then we read it
out at the bottom and it moves these uh
paddle and over time as I'll show you it
gets better feel free to go to the spike
stream and have a look at that but right
now what I want to discuss is yes it's
all well and good that a system may be
able to organize Its Behavior here in a
changing environment and this is
actually an example of a very successful
so these are actual neurons driving this
paddle so it's an example of one of a
one of our most successful cultures but
by no means is it a uh you know a weird
exception we do see the sort of better
performance fairly often again there is
variation of course
and one of the ways that we he wanted to
investigate this initially was this idea
of the free energy principle which I'm
sure many of you are familiar with so
I'm not going to go into it in a great
amount of detail but I will provide kind
of like a higher level summary of it
here and the key things that we can sort
of boil it down to in in a very
oversimplified sense essentially it
means that what we want to do with the
frenzy principle it suggests that there
is an innate imperative or a system to
actually match a prediction that it
makes to incoming sensation and it's
going to be phrased in Bayesian terms
and there's a lot of implications one
can take from that and you know I love
this picture that um carlston wrote up
in his uh or developed as part of his
Nature Neuroscience reviews uh
article if you haven't seen Reddit it's
a great article it covers a lot of good
stuff but simply between the linkages
between the different levels of the
system and of course like it is in like
one of the strong Arguments for it is
that being able to predict and act in
your environment is theoretically
necessary so and the other like
implication of course is that there
needs to be a statistical boundary
between the internal and the external
which is called a marker blanket and
we're going to touch on that a bit more
later
um diving into the notion of active
inference uh via the free energy
principle uh formerly it's sort of been
stated that this is a process of
minimizing variational free energy
through action and perception
uh and essentially what it's saying here
is that a living organism is going to
actively generate this internal model of
the external world and then align those
models and
broadly speaking there's two ways we can
do that either perception or action so
if I use my cell phone as an example
before if I reach over pick it up uh
what I've done is I've created a model
in my head based on the visual
information I've received uh where the
cell phone is I've reached over I've
picked it up very good my perception
matched matched my reality let's say
though that I didn't and I dropped it as
I tried to pick it up well what could I
do either I could get better at
liquid you know predicting the world uh
and say like when I reached when I reach
I will always drop my cell phone or you
know I could get better at defining
where it is in the world all what I
could do is get better at the actual
reaching action and really when you boil
down to it these are the only two ways
that A system can get better at
predicting its environment either
through getting better prediction or
getting better control in the
environment and so for our cell cultures
what we wanted to do was simply remove
one of these options so it's a very
simple implication from a very nuanced
Theory but
following that we sort of said if the
world became truly random something that
like we as people like you can't answer
most sizes too much because like we as
people can't really experience something
that's truly random
um but in a dish with random random
noise you you could at least approximate
it
um and so well that's what we did and so
we had these two options so what we then
said is that this is true what the cells
will do is actually change their actions
uh to make it Accord with the they're
the internal model of the world that
they have to decide and derive from the
sensory stimulation we feed them
so under this this model here that's
sort of represented in this picture that
you can see what we propose is that the
neural cells or the system will try to
minimize the difference between the
internal and the external world to
minimize the free energy of the system
I.E minimize that surprisal and
we kind of predicted whether reversive
is the right word or not uh it would
certainly we'd say that non-predictable
round of simulation should be saying
that the cells would try to avoid while
on the flip side if we gave them a
predictable stimulus when they did
something they liked that might be
reinforcing and again whether I put
these words in quotes because there's a
whole language question no one could a
question around what is it is a truly
aversive is it driving is it whatever
but for the sake of communication we
have to pick words right now so
hopefully you understand the uh the
context in which they're used and so
what we propose then is that the cells
should modify their activity to avoid
adopting a state in this case that's a
pattern of activity that would lead to
an increase in Surprise
and so what we could see here we set up
some experimental tests and we compared
a number of different methods so we
compared this control group this was
simply meteor in a dish that had the
stimulations and feedback applied to it
media in a dish should not be able to
learn without any cells we had an
insilico model that would drive the
pattern with random noise and
essentially this was to test the control
group you can think the media only
control group I should say you can think
of it as testing were we able to get
activities simply through our
stimulation the in silico was saying
could we get performance simply through
something in the system itself you know
making sure that the system isn't biased
in any obvious way then we had a rest
control group where this there were
cells in a dish but no stimulation and
this is asking the question left alone
will the spontaneous activity of neurons
because neurons always have activity
regardless of whether you're stimulating
them or not will that lead to better
performance again there's no reason it
should
if our system is set up properly of
course if there's a bias it would but
but that's what we're testing here and
then finally we had both Mouse and human
cells that were given the information
where the ball was were given feedback
and we're able to play the game and what
you can see is
basically this is a little hard to
interpret this graph if you don't stare
at heat maps all day but if you compare
say just the top right which is uh the
number of hits that are occurring in any
given minute by the minute on the the
x-axis you can see that it doesn't
really change too much over time for the
control group but compared and obviously
the other the in silicone the resting
controls are kind of the same as that if
you compare it to the mouse and say the
human cultures you can see quite a clear
difference here
and if you want uh more more asterisks
for significance because because who
doesn't love asterix's uh at least all
scientists love asterisks uh or other
other symbols of significance what we
can do is you can see over time uh this
control groups uh the media controlled
in silicone control the rest control
they they don't show any difference over
time a bit of variation But ultimately
no no real significant difference over
time in contrast to Mouse and the human
control of human cells uh both showed
learning over time and by the second
time point they are performed all the
other cultures of all the world cultures
all the other conditions I should say uh
interestingly the human cells even ended
up slightly outperforming the the mouse
cells and although I would be careful
not to over interpret this it was
interesting to note that uh We've run
this experiment a number of times and
this is a very consistent difference and
so it could be an interesting way to
start to investigate differences in the
future between species uh if one wanted
to set up a study more rigorously to
actually test us
and these results were replicated it
wasn't like we found one measure that
suddenly looked like performance and we
ignored the rest
we looked at a number of them you know
some of the other interesting ones the
stuff like the percentage of long
rallies where it's hit the ball more
than three times in a row so for four
plus in a row
um
and you can see here again significantly
did you know changes over the time for
the mouse and human cells nothing for
the others likewise the aces which is
kind of like tennis where they missed
the ball without even hitting it once
this decreases uh statistic
statistically significantly over time
for the mouse and human cortical cells
not for the others so much
uh so that's interesting but you know we
sort of say like well it's interesting
it shouldn't be surprising because we
know that neural cells are adaptive uh
and the fact you can see it in a dish is
cool but what what are the implications
what can this actually teach us about
how these cells are behaving and one of
the things people have looked at uh in
detail previously uh is functional
plasticity so what we looked at here is
of course we also assessed functional
plasticity and so that there was a
massive difference between the resting
uh State functional plasticity and the
gameplay functional plasticity
but what what does that actually mean
what does that actually look like going
Beyond just the fact that there's
plasticity occurring in the culture so
what you can do is you can look here at
just a correlation in the activity
between the cells in the motor regions
that I've shown you before and the
sensory regions and it's not too
surprising that whether or not they're
playing the game you have quite a high
degree of correlation the correlations
at rest are slightly stronger than the
correlations of gameplay
but what is interesting actually is if
you take the average correlation right
not just not just what is the overall
correlation but you actually break down
the average correlation per culture uh
and session what you do is you actually
get a far higher average correlation uh
between uh the sensory and motor regions
uh when they're playing the game then
when they're at risk this makes sense if
you need to coordinate your action with
incoming stimulation you need to have a
degree of correlation between where you
receive that action and the activity
there and where you're at your activity
output is going out but conversely if
you have in this case basically you can
think of it as two buttons even though
they're spread over four regions what
you would actually need to have is a
negative correlation or reduce
correlation between these regions uh and
if you look at the percentage of
exclusive motor region activity in this
graph which is where you have activity
in either the up or the down region and
bear in mind again these are
counterbalanced so this results actually
pretty interesting to see uh what you
see here is that during rest versus
gameplay you actually have a higher
degree of uh exclusive motor region
activity which would of course be
necessary for discrete control in One
Direction versus the other and that was
this was quite an exciting result
because it was really supportive sort of
that there is something quite Dynamic
and interesting going on uh in in the
way that these cultures are reorganized
interactivity and likewise this actually
just shows the degree that this
correlation decreases over time
with two linear regressions and you get
two very different linear regressions
over the first five minutes and the last
15 and we arbitrarily just based on some
early work decided to and again not
super arbitrarily but based on some
early work I should say we decided to
sort of split the games up into the
first and stabilize and so that was
quite supportive to suggest like what
we're seeing here is really the tapping
in of some of the key uh adaptive
properties of the neural cultures
and to take it further a bit more of a
bit more of a focus on the sort of free
energy implications here uh we can of
course reframe surprise it has a link
with information entropy
um and you know as for those of you
familiarism must be captured as a tail
just uh Divergence between the two
distributions
um of what might be occurring and so we
wanted to actually calculate here the
information entropy of the actual
cultures and now it's important to note
here this is internal to the cultures uh
both had gameplay and at rest and if we
didn't normalize it there's quite a lot
of variation going on in any given
culture but it becomes much clearer once
you do normalize it uh simply to to
baselines uh and you can see here that
when you give them random feedback so
one one thing I'll say firstly is that
the gameplay normally actually has much
lower information entropy than when
they're at rest
two when you give them random feedback
their information entropy
increases massively thereby suggesting
that these cells indeed should be uh you
know under the free energy principle
should be predisposed to avoid this
um and that that's actually what we saw
but what we're interested in is to say
well what if we tried different types of
feedback like how do we know like this
is all well and good
but how do we know that this type of
feedback is actually what's leading to
to these results because it could be it
could be anything uh and so we set out
and we introduced a few other control
conditions so this is our regular one
that I've sort of was showing you before
if it was a bit unclear hopefully this
helps to clear it up a bit uh when they
played the game they missed the ball
they get random unpredictable sensory
feedback when they hit the ball they get
predictable we then added something
called The Silent condition which is
when they missed a ball they basically
had all their feedback removed
And yet when they hit the ball nothing
they didn't get any additional feedback
the game just continued now it is
important to note of course that when
the game restarts after a miss the
direction of the ball is random so there
is still some Randomness in this game
but presumably less so than in the
normal stem condition and this can be
contrasted with this open loop or no
feedback condition
um they're sending thems in this case
basically where the game is played
information about where the ball is is
presented to the uh cells or the system
cells or controls whatever the case is
and then
uh but if they miss they don't get
anything changed if they hit they don't
get anything changed and so really it's
asking a question like will a culture
just play the game for the sake of
playing the game like there's no reason
it should but maybe they like maybe they
do so we wanted to test that and the
final condition we included here of
course is a rest condition and if this
helps to make it clear if you're more
graphical uh this can give you an
example so here you can see the ball
going up it hits to it and then you get
like a predictable stimulation here the
ball goes it continues and it gets hit
again and then it misses and it gets a
random feedback and then the game
continues silent in contrast you can see
that this random feedback here at the
same time point is removed for the
silent condition likewise there's no
predictable stimulation across the
culture and then the no feedback it's
just the ball becomes completely
predictable from the very first serve
there is no unpredictability in it at
all
uh and so when we look at the results
here and obviously if you're interested
you can go look at the paper because we
dive into this in in you know similar
detail as before but uh just in brief
what I'll show you is that here what
we've done is just compared it to rest
because it helps control the variability
a little bit
um and it makes it look a little neater
uh but essentially the stimulus
condition they outperform rest they
outperform their starting position over
time it replicates what we saw in the
first study and The Silent One there is
a very slight increase it doesn't reach
statistical significance but they do end
up also statistically slightly better
than the no feedback condition which
shows pretty much no learning compared
to rest at all
so that matches up pretty much with what
we expect to see like around the free
energy principle you know a condition
that gets a small amount of Randomness
shows a small amount of learning if you
want to do that but not a lot uh
something that gets a lot of random
information as a result of a an action
that we we deem undesirable shows a
greater tendency to avoid that action
and something that has no incentive to
behave in a particular way doesn't
behave in a particular way
so what was really interesting and
exciting for us also although I'll be
honest it made us stop for a few minutes
to actually think about why this has
happened was that when you look at this
normalized information entropy again we
got a replication that when you gave
them random feedback the the uh actual
internal information entropy goes up
with the silent condition the
information entropy also went up and in
fact even more so and we went why would
this be the case and of course what we
realized quite quickly was well neurons
left alone do fire spontaneously and
when you take a neuron from a stimulated
condition to an unstimulated condition
they do tend to re-engage with the
random spontaneous activity quite
vigorously straight away and so we went
and yet
it didn't show the same degree of
learning
so of course like I will say this is one
finding that absolutely needs to be
followed up more in the future and we
are doing that but it does have an
interesting implication in terms of
Markov blankets so I mentioned this
before I flagged it before and this is
why because I think this is one of the
really interesting results uh so to go
into more detail what a marker blanket
is is it's a statistical boundary that
can distinguish an internal state from
an external State and this can be at any
level so it could be at an individual
Neuron a cluster of neurons
um and nuclear distinct functional
region of the brain the whole brain the
body
in relation to the rest of the world or
what's outside it
and so the fact that as I was saying
that we see that the silent condition
even shows more random random uh or
Randomness or information entropy then
when we're actually providing external
random information into the system uh is
actually very very consistent with what
we know about the stochasticity of
spontaneous activity but what it does
also suggest is that cells will respond
differently to Randomness inside a
system versus outside a system
and that was a really exciting result to
sort of find like almost physical
evidence or like perhaps you know this
marker blanket like really exists of
course it it makes sense it exists like
theoretically there's a lot of reasons I
mean even just the simplest notion that
we can separate what our internal
thoughts are from someone's external
thoughts uh it's so not it's not
external thought someone's external
voice to us I should say uh suggests
that we need to have some sort of
barrier to distinguish these types of uh
structured information one internally
One external uh but seeing it was very
very interesting uh and so we also
wanted to of course extend beyond this
and sort of not just stop here and look
at what other interesting things might
be happening and you know one of the
other interesting findings that we've
we've recently completed and there's a
pre-print of this up now is this idea of
neural criticality and so what is
criticality for those who aren't very
familiar with it in brief it is this
state where a population's activity is
coordinated uh basically between two two
other states so you know physically you
could think of it at that point where
between where water becomes ice and
there's a point just in between which is
a transition to bring it back to the
brain you can think of it as a brain
connect firing rate could be either
highly coordinated rhythmic oscillatory
much as like when we sleep or in
Catatonia or it could be completely
disorganized like in some cases of
epilepsy and that then there's a middle
ground and there's obviously a quite a
you know it's a spectrum so there's
quite a lot of middle ground but the
closer you get to this sort of critical
transition point this is called
criticality and theoretically it's been
proposed to maximize uh give me there's
my timer telling me to take a break
it's theoretically it's been proposed to
act as a key criteria to maximize
information transmission and capacity
and what's also really interesting is
that it's been linked to a numbered
different cognitive behaviors although
the field is certainly a bit unclear
about what that is so it's been like for
example two responses to drugs working
memory attention one of my particular
favorites is cause of fluid intelligence
uh
but these Studies have some some
concerns with how they investigate it
and ultimately one of the biggest
concerns is that they're doing these you
know these these ones at least in uh
humans we have lots of compensatory
mechanisms you have to use uh fmri or
similar mostly fmri measures to actually
investigate it so there's a lot of
barriers in actually concluding this so
we set up a study to actually
investigate this and essentially again
to not go into too much detail about the
nuances we looked at three key different
metrics there's been a bit of criticism
in the field where people focus
predominantly on power laws power laws
can arise from noise alone so we wanted
to avoid that shortfall and look at
three different measures and so this is
this is sort of the setup we had we took
them we compared them either playing the
game or at rest which I described to you
before and then we looked at these
things called the the DCC the branching
Ratio or the shape collapse error and we
wanted to see how we could group them
foreign
my slides have Frozen
let me try to jump to the next one
alrighty so hopefully that's back for
everyone now let me just
there we go okay so what we saw here
really surprisingly was a very Stark
difference in in criticality uh across a
number of measures so you can just see
here basically the prediction between
the the rest and the active was it's
quite a just noticeably by eye very
different and of course that
statistically significant diving into a
bit more detail we could look at these
different measures and this is just some
quick overview of what those different
measures look like
um so the the DCC the branching ratio so
for example with branching ratio
critical systems sort of maintain the
number of uh uh sort of threads of
activity that might happen in a
subcritical system that variation will
die off over time in a supercritical
system it's going to continue to expand
up into a point and then there's a shape
collapse error of course which is
looking to see how you can collapse
different Avalanche shapes across a
given spectrum and then looking across
all of these we get quite strong long
statistical differences showing quite
clearly that when you have the system
embodied in an environment it's showing
this measure of criticality which is
very interesting
um and one of the interesting things for
this actually is that it shows that this
criticality is very fundamental and that
information input seems to to drive it
very strongly and to us this does seem
like a challenge suggesting that it is
in itself inherently a marker of some
sort of higher order
system
but of course I think the most
interesting thing is simply that we can
identify this and then what it does is
open up the possibility to further
investigate it with more nuanced tests
that were explicitly designed to
investigate criticality
but what was nice also to see like I
guess some suggestion that it does have
a role in some sort of information
processing in some degree is the fact
that he is also just showing you these
results in a slightly different measure
but looking at the correlations there
were some artistically significant
correlations between the different
measures of criticality
and the gameplay performance showing
that cultures that showed higher degrees
of criticality across all three markers
also had better gameplay performance in
this hitness ratio where they hit the
ball more often than they missed it
which was of course interesting to see
and does suggest that although
we think that because this was arising
in such a simple system it uh it was
such simple input that it's unlikely to
represent
um
or at least in of itself be a criteria
for intelligence per se that there
certainly is some link between
processing information and criticality
and if you want a more nuanced
discussion of this
um please feel free there's a there's a
pre-print up now while the papers going
through clear review we discuss it in
more detail there and finally what I
would say though is that just to sort of
really Hammer home the point that this
is a very fundamental property of these
cultures and that it is so drastically
different when they're playing the game
versus rest that when we wanted to
classify the cells based on criticality
metrics and performance as either
playing the game will rest
we were able to do this with a 98
success rate uh if you took into
performance and if you even if you just
ignored performance and you just looked
at criticality with random Forest we're
able to do this with a 92 percent
success rate of characterizing whether
they're playing the game or at rest and
that's that's obviously suggests that
this is very fundamental that one says
information input in these cells uh
they drastically reorganize their
activity and that's really interesting
of course one of the questions that we
also get asked a lot when we sort of put
out this early work was a lot of people
would say ah but who cares it you know
we literally had someone write a comment
uh
one of the peer reviewers not in the uh
actually at one of the points said to us
you know but you can't this can't
actually do anything better than
reinforcement learning so how can you
conclude anything about biology which
was a surprising comment to get
um but what what you know we wanted to
do and said fair enough like you know we
think there's plenty you can learn about
biology whether or not it does better or
worsen reinforcement learning but it's a
fair question like does this do you know
performance wise can it do anything
interesting compared to reinforcement
learning we know that if you run
reinforcement learning enough you will
get superhuman performance with the game
of pong they will solve it they'll beat
humans that's fine they can do the same
with protein foldings chess go that's
that's all well and good but that does
that mean that there is no room for a
biological system uh when it comes to
this so what we wanted to do was
actually compare it for sample
efficiency because that is of course
something that reinforcement learning uh
struggles with greatly so what we did
was we compared three different deep
learning algorithms dqn a2c and PPO with
three different types of information
input and against our biological
cultures to see how they performed and
so just showing you here some results
where we took the image Vector which had
a CNN to run and process it and then
feed it into the the dfrl algorithms
what we're able to see actually
um was that a mouse in human cells which
are here in blue and orange
significantly outperformed and out
Learned
dqn was was pretty much always the
lowest performer which is fine we know
that it's very sample and efficient but
even more sample efficient algorithms
like a to c and PPO also failed to show
the same degree of performance even
though they started higher for whatever
reason we could never quite figure out
to some Quirk of the algorithm they
never showed the same degree of learning
and this was again mimicked across
multiple comparisons but what was
brought up to us was this idea of saying
well there is of course the character
dimensionality so what you're doing is
you're feeding in a I think it was a 40
by 40 image Vector uh to these these the
Deep reinforcement learning uh and of
course it's going to take them longer to
converge they have to deal with more
information and we went you know what
that's a fair point so what we did was
run it even simpler
and we came out and we said all right
what we'll do is we'll feed them vectors
of Simply you know four Vector uh Matrix
of where the paddle is and where the
ball is and that will be much simpler
and closer to the game plane so we fed
that into them and what we saw was
actually they performed us with less
information
uh and of course these are the the mouse
and human image time because we can't
alter the information put in this way it
was a post-hoc party
the actual Mouse and human cortical
cells but yeah they did even worse
across multiple matter
and we found again they're outperforming
it a little more information than what
the uh also getting because their sales
are really only just received in the
ball position we don't we're not yet
able to encode proprioception because
the disk brain system is very simple and
you know although we would argue again
like this sparsity of information should
surely make it harder not easier with
less information and certainly with our
initial pilot testing we found that the
more information you gave them the
better they could do we again said fair
enough let's change the change the
information and put to the uh
reinforcement learning algorithms give
them the simplest possible information
that matches as close as we could
possibly do to what the cells are
getting and see how they performed and
again they performed even worse
suggesting that in fact more information
is probably helpful uh and certainly
what we could show here is that like yes
there is certainly something interesting
going on in neural cells and the way
they're able to process information and
it comes back to this quote that I love
so much which is to say that like if the
human brain or in this case even a
simple collection of neurons in a dish
was so simple that we could understand
it we might be so simple that we
couldn't uh and you know we like to
think that the tools we're building such
as this is going to help us to actually
simplify it enough that we'll be able to
unpick and start to understand the
nuances behind this but
one of the nice things that we're able
to show is that even without fully
understanding all the nuances of what's
going on inside a dish like this we can
see that it does have something strange
distinct traits in terms of intelligence
that have promising advantages for
information processing above and beyond
what's going on in reinforcement
learning and we really think this
happens home that this is going to be a
powerful tool to investigate these
features in more detail
so as a as sort of a summed up
conclusion uh what we're able to do with
this system essentially is have a system
of real biological neural cultures that
can exhibit a very rudimentary form of
uh natural intelligence uh through their
inherent adaptive traits and these
adaptive traits uh like frankly quite
amazing to the extent and the variety
and diversity of what they're shown and
even with the data that we've really
generated we're only just scratching the
surface but there's a lot of potential
that they have and so simply by having
this closed-loop system of
electrophysiological stimulation and
recording via these
multi-electrode arrays we could embed
them into a or embody them into a
simulated World depending which term you
prefer and they could get better at
playing it and moving the paddle to
actually be able to perform the game uh
with quite a quite a consistent degree
of coordination with a faster learning
rate like then multiple reinforcement
learning algorithms and uh you know of
course this is as I said it's a lot of
work we're only just scratching the
surface and so one of the things we're
excited to do because we're we're
actually not an academic lab we're a
small startup based in Melbourne
Australia because we want to open this
platform up to everybody so if you have
a question or you think everything I've
just told you is completely wrong and
that neurons work in a totally different
way
that's fine you know reach out we will
in next year
um be opening up for Alpha Testing and
so the most exciting projects we'll be
supporting to have an early access to
this if you want to investigate the
properties of these neurons and you have
basic python or Java coding skills
you can access them virtually and code
them as an environment and see how they
respond and test it and you know go away
and write a paper sort of showing how
how you think that it should all work
based on actual data and this is because
we acknowledge this is a whole whole
industry like this or whole field of
research of course and so we want to try
and make these tools available for as
many people as possible and we're going
to make it as easy for you as possible
as well and it's going to be fairly
affordable
so that's that's the end of the talk and
uh of course it's not just me
um working on it there's a whole team
and a number of collaborators that we
work with these are just the
collaborators that sort of touch on this
work there are many other very valuable
people we work with that are expanding
in other areas and so and actually we're
fortunate enough that uh Professor Adele
razi who who's one of our closest
collaborators has actually been able to
join us today for the discussion part of
it uh and so if there are any
discussions really happy to to take
questions
all right
wow
well uh thank you very much for that
excellent presentation it gives us a lot
to
jump into
so perhaps a deal feel free to say hello
introduce yourself and add any general
remarks so that we can jump into some
more questions
yeah thank you Daniel great talk right
and as always you did uh it was
intuitive fools that there is so many
projects that you love is uh is really
doing amazing work so
um I'm based at Menasha University we're
not that far from the um cortical Labs
is
um yeah in the city really but it's a
Suburban at the main campus University
where we have this computational
systems near science lab and our lab is
using
brain Imaging and computational models
uh especially Dynamic causal modeling
and active infants as Frameworks to look
into the brain and try to understand
what's up you know um yeah how
um
one can look at little mechanisms of for
example how the brain implements
coordination for example uh for this we
think we we use as I said
um mathematical framework of divine
friends and also dynamical modeling so
that's basically what we are doing
um and happy to contribute to this
discussion it spreads um you know
um you know there and it should be uh
the one who should be talking more than
I would be gladly just sitting here and
listening to wonderful uh interaction we
already are having
awesome well
my first question just for context was
how did active inference come together
with this line of research were you
studying active inference and then
looking for an embodied system or was it
something like you were studying this
very interesting system and looking for
some type of framework to help you model
it
absolutely it's a great question and it
goes back it goes back historically so
um Andy kitchen actually who and uh and
and han han who's uh one of one of the
founders of the company uh they were
they were interested they were looking
for for ways to explore it and actually
a deal uh you you ended up having a
conversation with them I believe and
they were basically looking for
Immaculate of like how could we how
could we talk to the cells and they came
across active inference uh or did you
introduce them to active inference
um I would say that that Andy and Han at
that time that we are talking about late
2018 early 2019
um and they were already interested in
freeing the Japan support
um and but then I just moved to
Melbourne from from London in mid-2018
and I ended up giving a talk at Alfred
where cortical lab is a big incubated at
the time
um and I was discussing these uh these
ideas and it was kind of uh you know
um interaction that just happened
and then we thought yeah well okay
there's lots of synergy
and there we go uh we had uh we
workshopped some of the early ideas uh
at that time
um and thought about you know on and
Andy were very thinking about how to
actually what could be the first thing
that we should do which would then
um really uh showcase the power of the
discipline of course the discipline
exact name came later on yeah yeah
that probably has been sampling child no
no actually this Frame describe is a
name definitely goes goes to Andy as
well um okay I would have given it some
some sort of uh esoteric uh name that
everyone would have gone what the hell
is that so no it's a good call by Andy
to do that um yeah yeah but of course
like it does have a lot of really useful
features uh the whole active inference
framework uh that that make it quite an
ideal thing to test you know the whole
action perception cycle the fact that
there are like implications that you can
simply take and be able to test uh the
biological plausibility of it uh or make
it very useful as a system for us us to
adopt
um having said that though and like a
you know deal can attest to this like we
also well I think that it was uh I think
as a Neo Seth calls it uh maybe other
people call it that too it was a bit of
an adversarial uh collaboration in some
aspects as well because we were
interested in the idea but we had no
stake in proving or disproving it we
were simply testing it and so we had a
number of discussions as we went through
you know what if we see X Y and Z uh
what would be the states just kind of
challenge it not just support it and so
I think that's one of the things that
made it a really exciting collaboration
in in that there was a high degree of
skepticism amongst the team about pretty
much everything we did
um and I think that's what came together
and making quite a nice paper because we
were
like as everyone should be in science
but let's be realistic seldom are we
were trying to be our own worst critics
because we were trying to figure out
like what else could be explaining it
and you know and I think there are
interesting future directions we can
explore but certainly the results as
they are did find support that this only
is a key characteristic of how cells
respond
awesome so one preemptive question about
learning and then we'll
drive back towards active inference so
what kinds of mechanisms do the neurons
use to engage game mode and also to
learn are they changing their topology
in terms of their connectivity are they
changing what happens at synapses are
there changes happening inside of cells
what happens when the game mode turns on
and how does it actually improve
throughout the course of that experiment
uh look that's a great question and the
the reality is we don't have the full
answer for that yet
um most likely it's going to be a
combination of the latitude you
mentioned changes that are happening
potentially inside cells or inside
synapses I mean it's not necessarily too
useful to try and break those apart
the idea of like larger scale
morphological changes are less likely
simply due to the time scale that we see
and the fact that we don't typically
um although there will be some future
work sort of showing some other things
at the you know as we've moved on and
Advance with our work and we typically
in this study at least didn't see uh
learning across days so it's unlikely
there are massive changes in sort of
connectivity it's more likely that it's
functional changes in plasticity and how
they respond to information
and it could be a number of things like
it could be
um you know of course there's probably
some sort of relationship and balance
between heavy and homeostatic plasticity
long-term potentiation to long-term
depression and then you there's so many
mechanisms that you can break down to
look at how that is uh you know from you
know like one interesting candidate
could be looking at like phosphorylation
which interestingly takes I think about
five minutes to to translocate from from
inside to outside uh synapses and then
is known to alter long-term potentiation
uh
which would roughly Accord with that
time but this is something we need to
investigate more in the future
um higher level to that I mean a deal
might have some some ideas to sort of
discuss higher level uh than this you
know less reductive and more high level
yeah more more computational so
um yeah I mean you know we are really
interested in learning mechanisms uh and
especially uh formative and
transformative
um what uh the learning mechanisms
in artificial uh that we can mimic
inactive field neural networks that so
so one of the you know while we have the
biological chip which can learn can we
actually now understand how it's doing
this and can we in the short term you
know uh have
in a better artificial neural networks
of course the you know we have wrapped
in this team is taking to us that we
actually don't need that artificial
neural networks anymore uh we'll just
have the biological chips right
um so so that's that's exciting
um so we have been looking at you know
certain things some of the more um
unresolved problems in in deep learning
and in machine learning for example
um lifelong learning and continue
learning uh where we know that
um
artificial neural networks they break
down in in in in tasks where you have to
do multiple tasks Industries and they
could do very good uh human-like
performances on a single year task but
then uh you train them on the second one
and then they forget what they learned
in the first one unlike humans so it
could run swim speak without you know
forgetting what
um you know otherwise it will be a
catastrophic
um so that's one thing another thing um
you know credit assignment so one of the
bigger problems how do you actually uh
solve the credit retirement problem
which is again an also a long-standing
problem in deep learning that if so what
sort of uh choices uh we make that
result in uh rewards and future so what
uh and and and many a times what happens
there's a delay
there's a delay in recording what
behaviors resulted in the uh in the in
in the reward for example uh so so
looking at what elements and what
choices that we made that resulted in a
long-term gain is another problem that
that I I we really don't know right now
how do we actually going to but these
are bigger very big problems which are
unsolved and I think it just shows you
the the power of the dish braid system
that it can actually help us to you know
I think there's a real
um real opportunity here for us to
actually attack those problems as well
at the you know how level yeah as Brett
was saying
and I think it's it comes down to also
being like the right tool for the right
job so
reinforcement learning cnns can do
amazing things uh if you've got the data
to train them if you've got you know the
uh the rest of the setup that you need
and you want to use it for the right
purpose
are they very good for doing stuff in
Dynamic Real Time with limited data
fuzzy information
but so far no
um and so maybe like there will be a
case where we can take
some of the findings from how neurons
work and apply it in an algorithm in
itself
uh you know I know a name a deal and and
his his team are doing some amazing work
with uh you know building up active
imprints models uh and I think those
results are really going to you know I
think excite a lot of people just as
just as just as some flagging of some of
the work you're doing a deal I won't
mention anything else but it's going to
be really exciting I think for people to
see what's what's happening
um and
but likewise I do think that there will
be things that biology maintains
superiority over uh the question and the
nice thing about biology of course when
you talk about generalized intelligence
is we have no proof of principle that
generalized intelligence can arise out
of silicon Hardware
or Quantum hard you know Quantum based
Hardware
we do have proof of principle that it
can Arise at a biological wet wear our
brains and brains are flies of cats of
rats whatever uh show general
intelligence to differing degrees and so
to us it's like not a question of can
biology show generalized intelligence
but how do you get there and that's a
less speculative question not
necessarily an easier question to answer
it's not easier necessarily but it does
give you that ground truth it's the
thing in and of itself sort of answer
wow so much there in silico and in
principle systems can display open-ended
symbolic learning going back to the
turing machine
but for the kind of open-ended enacted
intelligence that we might be interested
in in settings like you described which
are real time fuzzy and with small data
and we could also add with a high risk
or survival threat those kinds of
settings we have empirical evidence
across the surface of the planet that
biological systems can make that happen
and we have zero empirical examples of
silicon chips making that kind of a
functionality arise so that's a very
interesting point
um
that kind of brings to this question
about the similarities and the
differences between the artificial
neural networks and the biological
structure and also between the
reinforcement learning Paradigm and the
active inference Paradigm in which
rather than maximizing a reward function
we are minimizing an expected free
energy or a variational free energy by
way of bounding surprise so in
describing the experimental setup
the reward
or rather the consequence of succeeding
or failing was you adjusting the
regularity of the input and in a
reinforcement learning Paradigm that's a
little bit of an unconventional
manipulation one might expect oh we'll
we'll add sugar or we'll add a dopamine
Agonist or an antagonist to the dish
to Signal the positive or the negative
valence directly kind of by putting our
our finger on the scale of the reward
function but rather you were able to
train and Learn by changing the patterns
of regularity of feedback so how does
active inference
have similarity and difference with
reinforcement learning in terms of the
way that we can use patterns of
regularity not just valence of
interventions in learning
I'll give an answer that I'm going to
pass over to a deal who who can dive a
lot more into the computational side of
it than than what I what I could
um what I would say though is that
there's a few things as well like one of
them of course is uh can you even adopt
a reinforcement learning Paradigm in a
dish
uh it's not like there was a choice
between the two because we don't have
access to a privileged reward Network
inside the dish to be able to say you
know good sales bad sales we you CL you
could like in theory Square dopamine in
but you can't continually Square
dopamine and you can't do it in a
spatial or temporal resolution that
that's accurate enough right it diffuses
slowly across media
we can't do it
um so for us we needed to find something
that was more fundamental
and I think that's an important point
and I think it's also interesting to
note like that there are studies that
look at the fact that you can mimic
changes that you see with uh electrical
information that you can also achieve
through like the application of small
molecules such as such as dopamine or
whatever neurotransmitters
um and the right stimulation can
increase long-term potentiation much in
the same way that say dopamine would and
so dopamine seems likely to be a tool
this is speculative of course but it
seems likely to be a tool that shortcuts
uh the the way that these systems work
in line with some broader imperatives
such as free energy minimization more so
than uh being something unique and
special it is unique and special in its
own right like in the way that it works
but it must be serving a more
fundamental function
um yeah I think that that's probably
like a good way then to sort of lead
into the differences between let's say
an active frame inference framework and
a reinforcement learning framework which
I think a deal would be best to best to
discuss yeah yeah
um great question Daniel uh first you
started with the differences in uh in
silico models uh artificial neural
networks and the biological neural
metrics so uh first of all as we see uh
the artificial neural network is a
um is a caricature of an actual
biological layer on
um it just mimics that you know it takes
an input uh you know and then gives you
an output there's a non-linear you know
function and then once you have many of
them
um you know and stack them up and and
make lists they can do amazing things so
this is like new artificial neural
networks just uh using the one of the
video uh
a cartoon of what a biological neural
network do it would do it it has a lot
more than that it has it is an extremely
complex uh biological uh you know things
so uh imagine now that uh you know we
can reuse all of the Power and all the
uh you know you know um when it comes to
what it can in terms of information
processing and then uh build systems how
powerful they will be
um as we know you know uh currently
these huge
um what we call uh what we call these
large scale language models for example
llms and and then all those fundamental
models that we have been you know seeing
uh with billions of parameters to train
them it requires a gigawatts of power
it's basically like a whole city can be
looked up with once they train not a
human brain is just using a you know a
small fraction of in area time and power
to do much more than what they could do
they still can't do so causal learning
causal reasoning problems very basics of
them uh involve that logical neurons can
do it you know ways whereas as we are
doing it right now we are having a back
and forth discussion and you know
um that a big is one of the most uh
sophisticated sophisticated and he age
neural network would not be able to
achieve uh even for a few few minutes
um so that's that's what we are looking
at there's an enormous
um you know uh opportunity that we have
to actually harness this power and do
amazing things
um now coming back to so that's you know
uh now coming back to active inference
and reinforcement learning now this has
been the uh this has been asked many
times and
um there are papers that colors it in
nothing new side it has a paper on on
where they look at
um you know however um
pnm what is Bala so I think active
influence is biologically plausible so
uh so the main difference is is that
when you are uh an active infant system
is is optimizing a single quantity it's
what we call the free energy of Asian
free energy and that gives you
um that gives you with a single
optimization function you are doing
perception planning and decision making
in the same with the same quantity so
um let me put this uh this in this way
uh you know things that how things have
happened over the past few decades that
we it has been always been about how to
optimize a function so once you have
let's say a value function a reward yeah
uh in reinforcement learning is all
about how best you can optimize this
quantity while what we are asking we are
saying that what is we are optimizing
not how we optimize so what is that
quantity and that's the relation for
energy that we're optimizing and it
gives you all of that in a single you
know compared to a the enforcement
Learning System that would require
multiple objective functions to optimize
so I think it's not biologically
attainable to have that so I don't think
uh and that's why the active inference
is
um is a is a unifying framework and it
probably would Rattle and offend free
um that you know that we think that you
know that active infants subsumes
um all those uh you know
um computational Frameworks like
reinforcement learning
um you know uh into a dynamic
programming and all those uh derivatives
uh because it is basically what the
brains are doing you know and and
they're doing it better than what uh you
know uh framework that we have been
using so far uh so I think there are
differences clear differences uh and uh
however having said that I would really
would like to to see uh in future and
probably we probably will have a dig at
it how you can actually mathematically
which is then become unambiguously show
um provide a proof that where these uh
you know
why active Infinity so that there's a
still this is still a gap there while we
could
um develop uh insular active insurance
agents and we can show them that they
are doing better than reinforcement
learning agents and then we have quite a
few
um there's a whole uh sort of work that
uh of my PhD student Ashwin Paul is
doing and the papers are coming where we
are comparing active influence agents
with
um with uh with the state of the art
means learning and learning you know um
networks um and we are showing of course
the the active inferences is is is is
doing better uh but the theoretical
proofs are still missing similarly like
how active inferences is is
what are the similarities and
differences for example I would be very
interested to know how it's different
from uh to durov's work and again Ashwin
is looking at that I am an alternative
paper VNS paper in 2009 which looks at
efficient computations optimal action
which has far reaching it they show that
you can um both in discrete and on
continuous settings
um you know they they have shown that
they algorithms can be dynamic
programming and in subject learning
based uh based algorithms uh what is
this uh what is how active inference is
different from Tish price go to
information bottleneck uh you know um
thing how how what are the links between
Universal pride and suleimanov all those
all those things guys too you know it is
it's it's really early days uh you know
uh what are the similarities the
differences
of of activations with all those big
Ideas which are therefore you know in
cerbernetics and another literature
funny many many many years uh for for
decades what are the differences and in
similarities so it's a good question we
don't have all the answers but
um you know all the yeah so so it would
be very exciting next week is uh looking
at all those big questions
I just wanted to Echo one point you made
and then ask a question from the chat so
in reinforcement learning what you
should optimize is almost treated as an
obvious question you want to win the
game you want more points that's the way
to win you want to stay alive then you
want to optimize survival so that's your
reward function and what to optimize is
kind of swept under the rug and then
there's this big question of how to
optimize it and that's what has led to
this enormous diversification of
different approaches and heuristics for
how to optimize and different gradient
descent methods and so on in
reinforcement learning
in contrast in active inference what to
optimize is actually known it's the
variational or the expected free energy
as exactly specified by the generative
model and we know how to optimize it
which is with a variety of locally
plausible biologically inspired update
rules for example message passing and
belief propagation so that's very subtle
but also paradigmatic difference which
is that the structure of what we're
going to optimize as our unified
imperative for perception cognition and
action the free energy functional has
methods and software packages that will
step by step convergently optimize it
and so the onus is actually to specify
the generative model in a useful way
rather than treating what should be
optimized as just a bygone discussion
and then go into all these questions
about implementation which are the parts
that actually differ the most across
systems so I think that's very
insightful I wanted to ask a question
from the chat from Michael
what would be the difference if you
change the electrode array to stimulate
differently for example instead of just
growing the neurons on top what if the
neuron synapsed with the electrodes so
what kinds of experimental setups are
possible and which ones are interesting
and how do you know and what do you
choose to do
I think the the first thing to say about
that good question and certainly as the
technology develops we'll be able to ask
these questions in
better and more interesting ways like
it's probably worth well you know I've
made this comparison before but I'll
make it again like the work that we've
done here is you know we we're excited
by it but at the same time like it is
probably equivalent to like the early
transistors made by Shockley you know
it's janky it's kind of ugly it does a
job but not without not without
limitations
um and so you know what we're really
excited in is as the community hopefully
come together and work on this
5 10 15 20 years maybe longer
um you know 70 years of continuous
development have led from a transition
to being a large
ugly thing to thousands of them you know
within every device that I can see uh so
that's like one thing I just say in
terms of like I will point out like that
the the neurons do in as much as they
probably ever can integrate with the
electrodes as is as you saw from that
picture I showed at the start they are
deeply integrated into the the electrode
like we cannot like we could not and let
the neuron survive remove them in any
meaningful way and keep that structure
so you got they would have to completely
like this is so share their structure
and most neurons won't survive that
um for very long anyway uh so they are
currently integrated like I mean synapse
so synapses work slightly differently uh
yeah there's a whole there's a whole
collection of traits like there is of
course electrical activity is a shared
language between neurons and and uh the
hardware and that's what makes it
possible to stimulate them with
electricity because it can it can sort
of mimic the change in ions across the
the membrane to stimulate Action
potentials which is how they then
communicate with electricity but an
action potential is of course trigger
the release of chemical signals and so
forth and so there's a lot that's going
on there and I think it's it's about
building the bridge it's not necessarily
about
[Music]
um
rather than quite the right word phrases
about the completely recapturing
everything that's unique to biology and
the hardware all unique to the hardware
in biology it's about where's the useful
bridge and synthesis
uh between them to elicit The Best of
Both Worlds and you know again it comes
down that right tool for the right job
but in this case it's like a different
circumstance like what's the right tool
to
process the information uh is it is it a
biological part is it the hardware part
and so when we communicating then what
we need to figure out and again this is
an open question like I'm not sure where
it will go but what we need to figure
out is like where what's the the best
way at the time of the technology we
have right now it's it's not trying to
replicate uh sort of
hardware-based synapses to do sort of
chemical communication although maybe in
the future it will be but yeah it's a
very interesting question and like the
basically answer is like we don't really
know where it could go and we don't know
where it would do
um as I mentioned in the talk like they
are incredibly plastic neurons we can
change the configuration we can change
the type of neurons we can move from 2D
to 3D and this is work that we have
ongoing now
um and I think that what we're going to
see is just an explosion of results as
as we start to make inroads in this area
um
saying that the neurons might not
survive the separation from their cyber
physical digital substrate reminds me of
the reality of some to all of us today
if we were also stripped from our
digital substrate many critical systems
also would not function and I think that
speaks to some of the recent work of
friston at all at verses with the idea
of the ecosystems of shared intelligence
where we're thinking about distributed
cognitive processes that are mediated by
interfaces and so some emitted data set
is received by another cognitive entity
on the other side of the blanket and
maybe it's person to person maybe it's
computer to computer or something mixed
or some augmented system but there's a
really tractable and elegant way to talk
about those heterogeneous systems so
even if in the local context one
algorithm or another out performs
another there's going to be an immense
value for using active inference and fep
to just talk about how to compose these
systems and so that's very important
insight
100 that's a really good point Daniel
like very valuable and I yeah it comes
down I think like fully agree with you
it comes down to like how do we phrase
and think about these even and that's a
challenge like even discussing what
these systems are and what they're
showing is a challenge right now and we
need to work on building up that
language together so we can can have
those useful discussions and figure out
how to how to leverage this distributed
Network that we're all I think it's
inevitable
as you know that you bring up that that
is where that's where we are and it's
we're only going to go deeper down that
direction
awesome just a little bit of some
questions on information as we head
towards the end it was a very striking
finding about the changes in information
Dynamics when gameplay was activated
versus rest as well as during learning
and also that's kind of analogized by
let's say a person in an fmri and
they're mind-wandering they're engaging
the default mode and then some task
comes on and the information Dynamics
sharpen and we associate that with the
mechanisms of attention so how did you
measure or quantify the information or
what do those informational measures
mean in the context of neural firing
patterns
um yeah that's a big question and it's
again it's something that that we need
to do more work at diving into to
actually unpick about what it actually
means at this point what we're limited
to look well
that's not entirely true we're not
learning what we did look at just first
the sake of time and complexity were
individual spikes in a given location
and so you can arrange that spatially
and temporarily and so what we've looked
at and we've dived into this more work
with our recent work with organoids as
well trying to pick apart
sort of the sub functional subunits of
computation or intelligence or whatever
word you want to use
um but yeah so essentially what it is is
it's the pattern of activity you're
seeing across time and space for a given
spike in a location versus the other
ones and so
there's a number of ways you can look at
this I think the really exciting stuff
that's coming out is around sort of
trying to break apart so people started
hydrogen husky models Etc they looked at
neural spiking and they were like how
does a single neuron Spike what makes a
single neuron Spike and they came up
with some rules that are mostly true but
now we know are kind of still wrong
because you know that many neurons
follow those rules and many do not and
some are circumstance dependent
um and then people sort of extended that
and they looked at how the given uh
system changed its activity over time
and then of course you can expand that
out and look at like how do pairs of
neurons and then trios of neurons and
grow that up into a whole population and
so what we've tried to do with this work
that I've sort of shared with you today
is look at that at a few different
levels and so depending the level
depends the the exact answer to like
what is information but
um essentially like the simplest answer
is it's the spikes that we can see in
this case going on and their
relationships to others spikes
I don't know deal might have more to to
expand on that
um no I think you have clearly you know
I think uh at some point we've also you
know as you mentioned we want to look at
those functional subunits considering as
as the as they as you know using up
those main field models using uh those
functional units um as little
populations and then you know uh
hopefully they emerges like in a few
functional subunits and then can we look
at the connectivity patterns using for
something like enable mass models you
know which have been used quite a lot
um something like a Jensen with models
but a bit more uh Dynamics in them
um and uh yes that would be very
interesting to see uh how the patterns
are emerging when neurons learn how
their patterns are fine patterns and and
connections and and then you know how
these are changing over time as more and
more learning is happening and that
would be something you know we are all
talking about lots of uh unknowns and
lots of very interesting directions that
one can take
um which makes it all exciting
and I think like our thinking also at
least my thinking has changed over the
course of looking at this
when I started out I I kind of thought
well an individual neuron is the
smallest functional unit theoretically
right so that's probably what's going on
and then they'll connect up
and then I realized well I think like
yeah it is a single neuron it's a
functional unit but so are two neurons
and three neurons and and the collective
you know uh you know exponential growth
as you go out to whole pattern at the
end of the day when we look at actually
at the levels we're looking at for
example criticality if you if you go to
the preprint we broke it down into areas
like sensory versus motor areas and we
found that they all kind of behave more
or less the same so does that mean that
on the dish we have one functional unit
or eight hundred thousand or everything
in between
and looking at looking at the organoid
stuff that would move to that that we're
not quite ready to share yet but like I
think what we can sort of start to
tentatively conclude from this work is
that it's it is indeed that answer of
like one to the combination of the the
everything and I think that's what makes
the biological systems and this is why I
emphasize it in my talk look at the
amount of connectivity and sort of
chaotic connectivity to some extent
um that's occurring Within These systems
and that gives you something that we
can't model with neuromorphic or with
algorithms
with any degree of
[Music]
uh with the same traits at least I think
I can say without being too
controversial with the same traits we
can't yet model that algorithmically yet
and I think that makes this interesting
as well
awesome one just remark on that before
kind of a closing discussion the Hodgkin
Huxley models were on large single
isolated neurons and so a theme I heard
you say multiple times was like the
right tool or the right model in the
right context and so when studying
sodium and potassium flows across the
membrane of a single isolated neuron
that is absolutely an appropriate model
and something that provided in immense
insights and then as you pointed out
especially if you're interested in
properties of systems and connected
neurons it's like a yes and like R
sodium flows but you could imagine
contexts where learning happens and the
informational pattern or the entropy of
a given neuron does change or it might
not change but the pair otherwise
relationship might change or the
pairwise relationship might not change
but some higher order relationship does
change and so that doesn't replace
mechanistic or smaller subunit based
models but rather we can broaden the
discussion to thinking even about the
environment like of the dish or of our
peripersonal space that these cognitive
systems are embedded in and talk about
distributed cognitive functions
without privileging the ecological or
the sort of atomic levels of explanation
yeah absolutely absolutely and thank you
for clarifying that if I if I sort of
implied otherwise yeah awesome no no
just to highlight because
um
they're uh despite the ring on the cover
of the active inference textbook there
isn't a single model to rule them all
and I think like it's really by getting
into the particulars of experiments and
also by speaking with researchers and by
talking about this kind of Cutting Edge
research that we see how pluralism in
the methodological and in the
explanations
actually plays out not just very
exciting
um so I guess just a uh closing question
and then we can just have any other
remarks
uh Michael asks in the chat
what should someone study or do to get
more involved with this research I'm an
undergraduate student interested in
pursuing this field for my career and
I'd love to work with cortical labs
um so I think it really depends the area
you want to want to go down like we're
always looking for good people to work
with and as I said before like this is
going to be a whole whole industry uh
and a whole field of research we we hope
and believe anyway
um so I guess you should pick what it is
that interests you in what you're
passionate about it's there's so much
stuff going on right you could study
electrical engineer you could study
Physics you could study software
engineering you could study Neuroscience
you can study stem cell biology
um anything in between uh
these are a multi-disciplinary highly
collaborative outputs
um you know I showed the team before we
have people from all of those Industries
and and others and it's only the
combination of this these these areas
that uh give rise to the chance to
actually make something that it's the
Gestalt right it's greater than the sum
of its parts and I think honestly that's
one of the reasons why we've had some
success coming from a sort of startup
industry focus is that that's not that
many of us and we don't have that much
money but what we do have is like an
amazing team of people to work with
amazing collaborators like a deal to
work with
um and we can bring it all together in
one spot and that's that's hard to do by
its nature and Academia like by its
nature Academia tends to Silo and you
have exceptions to that rule of course
you have like very highly collaborative
works that do come out of Academia
but they're always they are always I've
worked in Academia um side and they're
always at a distance those
collaborations they're not all Under One
Roof with one one goal and one purpose
so
this is something though Oh no just so
yeah please any general comments feel
free to respond to that and also just
any general thoughts you want to add I
was I was I was just saying I cannot
recommend enough cortical Labs uh they
are highly disciplinary
multi-disciplinary team with expertise
from cell biology to you know to
software engineering to real-time
interfacing to computational models and
and machine learning so uh you know
anything that you know your expertise
and you want to do there would be
something that that that's there and
really cutting edge and so
um yeah I think there's this whole
project you know it just shows you know
uh the whole breadth of things that we
can do from uh from neurons to sentient
behavior and I'm I'm petting my bags for
saying sent in sentence today which has
been said so
um and and I should say Brett is also
leading a you know the projects on on
that side which we didn't get chance to
talk about about the about the
nomenclature and all that that happens
with the semantic of sentence and
Consciousness and agency and all that
um so
um and and and and and and the whole
ethic side of thing so it's they're big
big uh opportunities and courses open uh
open challenges and and I think you yeah
like actually I do you make a good point
I should use this opportunity if I may
Daniel at least for two flag yeah we are
we are engaging in her paper
um so if you are interested in the words
that we use whether you think that we
use them correctly or incorrectly uh we
would invite anyone you know we've made
these offers before but it's a great
place to say it again reach out
um we are setting up and we will have a
formal invitation uh somewhat soon I
can't exactly say when because there's
so much going on at the moment but
fairly soon we'll have an invitation
come join us let's work together and
just like figure out what language we
want to use as a community because uh
then we can move towards actually
building building some stuff instead of
just being caught up with like what does
this word mean and that's going to be
necessary so yeah please reach out to us
yeah I'll just note one project at The
Institute which is the active inference
ontology where we've been developing
definitions and also translations across
languages of core and supplemental terms
and we use that to annotate papers we
make natural language descriptions of
mathematical formalizations and we we
totally agree that ontology-based
systems engineering for active inference
cyber physical systems is how we're
going to treat this with the respect and
also bring in the discussions around
ethics philosophy and so on so this
isn't a Linguistics debate that excludes
other fields this is like laying down
the dance floor so that we can actually
have a discussion that's inclusive and
meaningful going forward which is what
is so important yeah that's awesome I
gotta look this up I didn't know that
you guys had one of those I'm going to
have a look up later I'll uh I'll send
it to you in an email well thank you so
much
what an awesome line of research and a
December
surprise or treat for us so super
exciting and please always feel welcome
to just reach out and join for any other
time
awesome thank you so much Daniel for
having us and everyone watching all
right bye thank you
foreign